Farhana Shahid

Research Interests _____

My research interests encompass the diverse spectra of Human-Computer Interaction, Ubiquitous Computing, and Social Computing. I have broad interest in the design, use, and social impact of technologies that create sustainable outcomes for low-resource communities.

Education ____

Ph.D. in Information Science 2021 - Present

CORNELL UNIVERSITY

Advisor: Aditya Vashistha

M.Sc. in Computer Science and Engineering 2017 – 2019

Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology GPA: 4.00 out of 4.00

Advisor: A. B. M. Alim Al Islam

B.Sc. in Computer Science and Engineering 2013 - 2017

Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology GPA: 3.74 out of 4.00

Advisor: A. B. M. Alim Al Islam

Appointments _____

Cornell UniversityIthaca, New YorkGRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANTJun 2021 - PresentBrac UniversityDhaka, BangladeshLECTURERMay 2018 - May 2021Eastern UniversityDhaka, Bangladesh

Sep 2017 - Apr 2018

Academic Awards

LECTURER

2020 **Distinguished Paper Award**, IMWUT Volume 3

2020 Honorable Mention Award, CSCW2020

2016 **University Merit Scholarship**, Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology

2015 **Dean's List Award**, Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology

2015 First runner up: Poster Presentation Session, Esonance, Islamic University of Technology

2012 Champion: Science Olympiad, Inter College Science Festival, Holy Cross College

2011 First runner up, 4th Bangladesh Chemistry Olympiad

2011 **Secondary School Merit Scholarship**, Education Board of Dhaka

Publications

JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

- 1. **Farhana Shahid**, Wasifur Rahman, Mohammad Saifur Rahman, Sharmin Akther Purabi, Ayesha Seddiqa, Moin Mostakim, Farhan Feroz, Tanjir Rashid Soron, Fahmida Hossain, Nabila Khan, Anika Binte Islam, Nipi Paul, Ehsan Hoque, and A. B. M. Alim Al Islam. 2020. Leveraging Free-Hand Sketches for Potential Screening of PTSD. In *Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies*. Vol. 4, No. 3, Article 94 (September 2020).
- 2. **Farhana Shahid**, Shahinul Hoque Ony, Takrim Rahman Albi, Sriram Chellappan, Aditya Vashistha, and A. B. M. Alim Al Islam. 2020. Learning from Tweets: Opportunities and Challenges to Inform Policy Making During Dengue Epidemic. In *Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction*. Vol. 4, No. CSCW1, Article 65 (May 2020). **CSCW Honorable Mention Award (Top 5%)**
- 3. **Farhana Shahid**, Wasifur Rahman, Anika Binte Islam, Nipi Paul, Nabila Khan, Mohammad Saifur Rahman, Md Munirul Haque, and A. B. M. Alim Al Islam. 2019. Two Tell-tale Perspectives of PTSD: Neurobiological Abnormalities and Bayesian Regulatory Network of the Underlying Disorder in a Refugee Context. In *Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies*. Vol. 3, No. 3, Article 101 (September 2019). **PIMWUT Distinguished Paper Award**

THESIS

1. Leveraging Features from EEG and Free-Hand Sketches for Effective Diagnosis of Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder, M.Sc. Engg. Thesis, In Department of Computer Science and Engineering, BUET, 2021.

Teaching Experience ____

COURSE INSTRUCTOR

- · Computer Graphics (Spring 2021, Fall 2020, Summer 2020, Spring 2020, Fall 2019, Summer 2019, Spring 2018)
- Pattern Recognition (Fall 2020, Summer 2020)
- Artificial Intelligence (Spring 2020, Fall 2019)
- Object Oriented Programming (Fall 2019, Summer 2019, Spring 2019, Fall 2018, Summer 2018)
- Digital Logic Design (Spring 2020, Summer 2018)
- Algorithms (Summer 2019, Fall 2019, Summer 2018)
- Data Structures (Summer 2019, Summer 2018)
- Operating Systems (Spring 2018, Fall 2017)
- Mathematical Analysis for Computer Science (Fall 2017)

COURSE COORDINATOR

- Computer Graphics (Spring 2021, Fall 2020, Spring 2020, Fall 2019)
- Pattern Recognition (Fall 2020, Summer 2020)
- Artificial Intelligence (Summer 2020, Spring 2020, Fall 2019)
- Object Oriented Programming (Fall 2020, Fall 2019)

MENTORING

UNDERGRADUATE STUDENTS

- Takrim Rahman Albi
- · Shahinul Hoque Ony

Services_

REVIEWER

2020–21 ACM Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI)

2021 ACM Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW)

2020 ACM Transactions on Computing for Healthcare

UNIVERSITY SERVICE

2019–20 AI, ML, and NLP thesis panel, Brac University
2019 Course curriculum update, Brac University
2018 Semester planning, Brac University

VOLUNTEER

2021 CHI 2021, Japan (Online)

2015 National High School Programming Contest, BUET

ORGANIZING COMMITTEE

2018 5th Eastern University Math Olympiad, Eastern University

Selected Talks_

CONFERENCE TALKS

Oct 2020 Learning from Tweets: Opportunities and Challenges to Inform Policy Making During Dengue

Epidemic, CSCW 2020

Sep 2020 Leveraging Free-Hand Sketches for Potential Screening of PTSD, UbiComp 2020